Guide to the Henry Austin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Austin papers
1851-1865
MS 1034
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(10 boxes)
The papers consist of architectural drawings and specifications for domestic, religious, and public buildings in New Haven, Connecticut, surrounding environs, and elsewhere. Included also are the architect's watercolor sketches of proposed buildings and two licenses to practice architecture (1864-1865.)
Austin, Henry, 1804-1891
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by Yale University through gift and purchase between 1902 and 1942, and 1990; transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from Beinecke Rare Book Library in 1979.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Austin Papers are composed of architectural drawings, design sketches, specifications, and photographs for buildings by Henry Austin and others. These materials represent only a fraction of the work Austin created during his long and productive architectural career.
The Yale University Library acquired the bulk of the Austin Papers through gifts and purchases between 1902 and 1942. George Dudley Seymour was one of the principal contributors of materials. The papers were stored in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library from 1963 until 1979, when they were transferred to the Manuscripts and Archives Department. In 1990 Peter Hale and John Kirby donated an additional eight items to the papers.
At the beginning of the papers, there are four boxes which contain watercolor design plates from two formerly bound volumes titled "Dwelling Houses, Stores, Banks, Churches and Monuments" and "Churches, Mansions and Villas." While the designs in the volume "Dwelling Houses" are generic, some of the designs in "Churches" actually specify the buildings for which the design was used. These include railroad stations in New Haven, Plainville, and Collinsville, Connecticut; residences in New Haven, Wallingford, New Britain, and Waterbury, Connecticut; and churches in Kent, Plainville, Portland, and Northford, Connecticut. The first pages in this volume include an index to all drawings in the volume.
The papers also include several additional drawings and specifications for residences in New Haven and Wallingford by Austin, as well as a few drawings which cannot be identified as Austin's. Photographs of the house designed by Austin for Ruggles S. Morse (Victoria Mansion) in Portland, Maine and Austin's licenses from the Internal Revenue Service are also in the papers.
The papers include a set of black and white photographic negatives of the drawings in the two design books, as well as of the drawings for the house on Chapel and Howe Streets in New Haven. The papers also include color slides of the drawings in the two design books (Box 9). These sets may be used to obtain copies of the originals, since no photocopies may be made from the original drawings. A duplicate set of the color slides is available for viewing in the Slide Collection in the Art and Architecture Library.
In order to protect the master set of color slides from excessive handling, Box 9 has been restricted and will not be made available for general research. Readers wishing to order a copy of a drawing should cite the title of the volume in which the drawing appears, using the abbreviation "CMV" for "Churches, Mansions, and Villas" and the abbreviation "DHS" for "Dwelling Houses, Stores, Banks, Churches and Monuments." To insure a proper identification of the matching slide, the reader should also include the design number, plate number, and page number as they appear on the drawing. For example, the first drawing in "Churches, Mansions, and Villas" would be indicated as CMV:I, I, 1, for design I, plate I, page 1.
New copy negatives made from the slides of the drawings are housed in box 10. As additional copy negatives are made they are added to this box. The reader services staff maintains a listing of the existing copy negatives.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Austin, son of Daniel and Adah (Dorman) Austin, was born on December 4, 1804 in Mt. Carmel, Connecticut. By the time he was fifteen, Austin was employed as a carpenter. He worked for Ithiel Town, who had opened an office for the practice of architecture in New Haven about 1810. Austin was able to avail himself of Town's fine architectural library in order to further his training in architecture.
In 1836, Austin opened an office of his own. In 1842 he was commissioned to design a library for Yale College, modeled after King's College Chapel at Cambridge, England. In designing this building, Austin was assisted by Henry Flockton, an Englishman then employed in his office. Another notable design of Austin's was the massive brown-stone gateway (1845-1848), in the Egyptian style, of the historic Grove Street Cemetery, New Haven. In 1861 Austin was commissioned to design a City Hall for New Haven, in which he was assisted by David Russell Brown of his office. This building is in the Italian Gothic style. Among Austin's other New Haven buildings were the old Railway Station at the intersection of Union and Chapel Streets; the old New Haven House; the Cutler and Hoadley Buildings; the Yale, Tradesmen's Mechanics, and New Haven Savings Banks; Eaton School; and Trinity Church Home. He built so many private residences that it was said that almost every street in New Haven bore marks of his taste. Most of these were in the then fashionable so-called Tuscan or Italian style. Austin also built many churches throughout the state and elsewhere and designed the monument erected in 1846 in Coventry, Connecticut, to the memory of Nathan Hale.
Many men trained in Austin's office in the fifty-five years of his professional life, and he was known locally as the "Father of Architects." Austin died on December 17, 1891.
Based on: Dictionary of American Bioqraphy. New York, 1943. pp. 432-433
Conditions Governing Access
These records are available for research.
Architecture -- Notebooks, sketchbooks, etc.; Architecture -- Connecticut -- New Haven; New Haven (Conn.); Architects; Austin, Henry, 1804-1891; Dickerman, Charles, 1816-1897
- Inventory
  - Dwelling Houses, Stores, Banks, Churches and Monuments, 1851
    - Title Page (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Design I, Plates I-VIII (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Design II, Plates I-IV (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Design III, Plates I-IV (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Design IV, Plates I-VI (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Design V, Plates I-II (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Design VI, Plates I-IV (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Design VII, PLates I-II (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Design VIII, Plates I-II (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Design IX, PLates I-II (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Design X, Plates I-III (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Design XI, Plates I-III (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Design XII, Plates I-III (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Design XIII, Plates I-IV (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Design XIV, Plate I (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Design XV, Plate I (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Design XVI, Plate I (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Design: House, 4 plates. pp. 52-55 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Design: House, 3 plates. pp. 56-58 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Design: House, 4 plates. pp. 59-61 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Design: House, 2 plates. pp. 62-63 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Design: House, 3 plates. pp. 64-66 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Design: House, 2 plates. pp. 67-68 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Design: Church, 4 plates. pp. 69-72 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Design: Cemetary, 2 plates. pp. 73-74 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Churches, Mansions, and Villas, [ca. 1850]
    - Index (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Design I, Plates I-III: railroad station at New Haven (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Design II, Plates I-II: residence of Moses Y. Beach, Wallingford, CT (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Design III, Plate I: hotel (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Design IV, Plates I-IV: dwelling house for Willis Bristol (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Design V, Plates I-II: residence for Nathan Peck, Jr., New Haven, CT (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Design VI, Plates I-III: residence of I. H. North, New Britain, CT (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Design VII, Plates I-II: residence of J. D. Dana, New Haven, CT (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Design VIII, Plates I-II: residence of Philo Brown, Waterbury, CT (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Design IX, Plates I-II: dwelling house (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Design X, Plates I-IV: residence of John P. Norton, New Haven, CT (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Design XI, Plates I-II (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Design XII, Plates I-III: residence of Thomas C. Pitkin, New Haven, CT (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Design XIII, Plates I-II: dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Design XIV, Plates I-II: dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Design XV, Plates I-II: dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Design XVI, Plates I-II: dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Design XVII, Plates I-II: Italian villa (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Design XVIII, Plates I-III: gothic villa (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Design XIX, Plates I-III: dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Design XX, Plates I-II: gothic dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Design XXI, Plates I-II: gothic dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Design XXII, Plates I-II: gothic dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Design XXIII, Plates I-II: residence of James E. English, New Haven, CT (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Design XXIV, Plate I: residence of Georg Gabriel, New Haven, CT (Box 3, Folder 49a)
    - Design XXV, Plate I: dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Design XXVI, Plate I: dwelling house (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Design XXVII, Plate I (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Design XXVIII, Plates I-V: Mechanics Bank, New Haven, CT (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Design XXIX, Plate I: entrance to the New Haven Cemetery (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Design XXX, Plate I: cemetery gateway (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Design XXXI, Plate I: railroad station, Plainville, CT (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Design XXXII, Plates I-II: railroad station, Collinsville, CT (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Design XXXIII, Plates I-IV: circular church (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Design XXXIV, Plates I-IV: Congregational Church, Kent, CT (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Design XXXV, PLates I-III: Congregational Church, Plainville, CT (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Design XXXVI, Plates I-IV: congregational Church, Portland, CT (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Design XXXVII, Plates I-III: Congregational Church, Northford, CT (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Design XXXVIII: windows, doors, and trimmings (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Design XIL (sic): windows, doors, and trimmings (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Design XL: windows, doors, and trimmings (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Design XLI: windows, doors, and trimmings (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Design XLII: windows, doors, and trimmings (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Design XLIII: windows, doors, and trimmings (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Design XLIV: windows, doors, and trimmings (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - End page (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Chapel and Howe Sts. house, New Haven, CT: drawings, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
    General
    See also: box 6, folder 77
  - Charles Dickerman buildings, New Haven, CT: drawings by Rufus G. Russell, Circa (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Simpson House, Wallingford, CT: measured drawing notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Unidentified residences by Austin: drawings, undated (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Bank building, New Haven, CT: drawings by Brown and Stilson, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Unidentified residences, architects not specified: drawings, undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Chapel and Howe Sts. house, New Haven, CT: specifications, undated (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Charles Dickerman buildings, New Haven, CT: specifications, Circa 1857-1864 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Almer Hall (or Hull) house, Wallingford, CT: specifications, undated (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Ruggles S. Morse house (Victoria Mansion), Portland, ME: brochures, photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Noah Porter house, New Haven, CT: specifications, [before 1871] (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - United States Internal Revenue: licenses, 1864, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Churches, Mansions, Villas: copy negatives of plates (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Dwelling Houses, Stores, Banks, Churches and Monuments: copy negatives of plates (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Chapel and Howe Sts. house: copy negatives of drawings (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Victoria Mansion: copy negatives of photographs (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Churches, Mansions, Villas: color slides of original watercolor drawings (Box 9)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 9 of color slides is restricted due to physical condition.
  - Dwelling Houses, Stores, Banks, Churches and Monuments: color slides of original watercolor drawings (Box 9)
  - Copy negatives made from slides in box 9 (Box 10)